[snorts]
>> War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's [music] invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history [music] of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price [music] of empire.
With the end of the Spanish Civil War,
both of the countries of the Iberian
Peninsula were controlled by fascist
dictators. [music]
Italy had been ruled by such a dictator,
Benito Mussolini, for more than 15 years
and now [music] the rest of Western
Europe, most of Scandinavia, and much of
Central and Eastern Europe was flying
the swastika. [music]
East, the Soviet Union under Joseph
Stalin, carefully observed the terms of
its treaty with Hitler, to whom it
shipped supplies of food and other
material.
But the greatest empire in the world was
undefeated and defiant.
The Battle of Britain, their Prime
Minister had told them, is about to
begin.
Defiance, however, does not come cheap.
Banker to the world at the beginning of
the 20th century, 50 years later,
Britain would be the most indebted
nation to the tune of $40
Food rationing had been progressively
introduced since January 1940. Rationing
had been introduced in Germany in August
1939, the month before the invasion of
Poland.
As the war went on, the vast majority of
Britons, including more than half of the
manual workers, had their own piece of
land, their garden or their allotment.
The British reliance on imported food
was almost halved.
But not everything in the British Isles
was as spirited or good-hearted.
>> [music]
>> The poet T.S. Eliot wrote to a friend,
"We are involved in an enormous
catastrophe,
which includes a war."
He may have been thinking of the
deliberate policy of misinformation
designed to confuse spies [music] and
traitors, which spread fear through the
population, spawning a whole catalog of
invasion alarms in which parachutists,
variously dressed as nuns, priests, and
policemen featured, not to mention
[music] those in sky blue uniforms with
transparent parachutes who floated
invisibly to earth.
As early as May the 12th, the tabloid
Sunday Pictorial was asking if the
government had considered training
golfers in rifle shooting to eliminate
stray parachutists.
These scenes, multiplied [music] a
hundred times, show how our men have
been prepared for the defense of
Britain.
A German-Swiss resident of the London
Borough of Kensington was arrested for
puffing on his cigar and pointing the
lighted end at the night sky. He was
clearly signaling to enemy aircraft.
Many stray dogs, less fortunate, were
shot on suspicion of carrying messages.
On the 23rd of May, Sir Oswald Mosley,
who had led the British fascists during
the 1930s with some huffing and puffing
but little electoral success, was
interned. On the 31st, General Ironside,
Commander-in-Chief Home Forces, reported
"Suspicious men moving at night all over
the country." And on July the 2nd, he
reported "There is signaling going on
all over the place."
But he lamented that no evidence had
been found of fifth column activities or
weapons of mass destruction.
In fact, though many stories from death
rays to parachuting nuns circulate to
this day, the evidence to support them
is as threadbare as evidence for the
tooth fairy.
Under pressure to form some sort of home
defense, the Secretary for War, Anthony
Eden, went on the radio on May the 14th
to announce the formation of the Local
Defense Volunteers or LDV,
said by some to stand for look, duck,
and vanish.
This questionnaire is addressed to
civilians who are not in armament
factories or in government service.
Have you joined the Local Defense
Volunteers?
The LDV formed groups associated with
social and sporting clubs and factories.
By July, 1 and a quarter million men had
joined, but they were not well supplied
with weapons.
When I started to form the Home Guard,
which was the LDV,
I joined them. I was 15 when I joined
them.
We got a bit of this and a bit of that,
and then finally you got your rifle. The
ones we were given was a Ross rifle.
It was a Canadian rifle that only held
five rounds.
Churchill insisted that the LDV be
renamed the Home Guard. Eden was
annoyed. He had had 1 million LDV
armbands printed.
Well, I was at school at Dulwich College
and not working very hard because I was
spending most of the evenings in the
Home Guard as a dispatch rider
uh and learning how to smoke and drink
and all the rest of the things.
Jack White was keen to play his part in
the Home Guard, but his application was
rejected because born the son of Russian
Jews, he was classed as an alien.
In the First World War, Jack White had
been awarded the highest decoration for
valor, the Victoria Cross. He was not
classed as an enemy alien or interned.
2,000 aliens living near the coast were
rounded up and others followed.
Churchill said that it was necessary to
[music] collar the lot.
In contradiction of its popular postwar
image, the Home Guard was a serious
reserve.
It fired shots in anger with several
kills to its credit in anti-aircraft
duties. Its patrols freed regular army
units for other work, and it housed, or
rather disguised, lethal groups of
trained commando-style personnel tasked
with murder and mayhem in the event of
an invasion.
Guard units also provided the enemy in
training situations.
More than one new recruit reported on
being captured by First World War
veterans more adept at soldiering than
they were.
We did all sorts of classes and things
for about a month
and fighting against the Home Guard.
And people took people thought Home
Guard was a joke, but they weren't. I
was captured by them twice.
And I thought I was a clever soldier.
They were on the ball.
The plan for Britain's defense, agreed
to on June the 12th, drew a line south
from Edinburgh to the Medway.
Another west from below London to south
of Bristol, an area further defined by a
number of stop lines.
Within these defined areas, anti-tank
ditches were dug and concrete pillboxes
built, and everyone waited.
Winston Churchill waited with
unquenchable optimism.
His mother was American. His belief in
the onward march of the English-speaking
peoples was well documented, and his
optimism was sustained not by confidence
in British arms, but by the conviction
that America, inextinguishable and
inexhaustible, would come in.
The greatest boost to Churchill's belief
in salvation across the Atlantic came in
August in one of the key moments of the
war.
The American Congress would not allow
neutrality to be breached by the supply
of war material to either side without
payment.
Opinion polls registered American
support for involvement in the war at a
mere 8%.
Roosevelt found a way. It was called
Lend-Lease.
Payment in kind, Britain made over naval
bases in her [music] West Indian
possessions to the United States.
Or payment later.
And Britain was obliged to pay. It took
50 years.
Churchill called Lend-Lease a long step
towards America coming in on our side.
Two days after the signing of the
Lend-Lease agreement, the 15th of August
was Adler Tag, Eagle Day, which the head
of the Luftwaffe, Reichsmarschall
Göring, nominated as the start of the
critical phase of the Battle of Britain.
The German air offensive that sought to
achieve control of the skies over
southern England preparatory to an
invasion.
In one respect, the advantage had
already moved from Germany to Great
Britain.
In early 1940, Britain had been
producing 256
fighter planes a month. Winston
Churchill, recognizing the urgency of
improving production, appointed the
Anglo-Canadian newspaper proprietor,
Lord Beaverbrook, Minister for Aircraft
Production. And so I beg all of you,
everywhere, to speed the tank.
Speed the defenses of Britain.
Under Beaverbrook's management,
production for the month of July climbed
to 496.
An article in Time magazine in 1940 drew
attention to his record and presciently
noted that this war is a war of
machines. It will be won on the assembly
line.
Importantly, the British assembly line
was not just turning out lots of
aircraft, but good ones.
These were the Hurricanes and Spitfires
that would write their names into the
history books.
Britain deployed other tools that would
be vital in the battle ahead.
Cryptologists, famously installed at
Bletchley Park, a country estate outside
of London,
decoded Luftwaffe signals that gave
warning of planned sorties.
The work of a British meteorologist
between the wars was critical in
developing the screen of radar stations
that was vital to British air defense.
His name was Robert Watson-Watt, and it
was under his leadership that the design
and installation of aircraft detection
and tracking stations, called Chain
Home, made possible the early warning of
incoming squadrons.
It was not, of course, all high-tech.
The defense of Britain also relied on
the keen eyes of 30,000 watchers peering
through binoculars at 1,000 posts
throughout the country.
Like Britain, Germany had first-rate
aircraft, but they were not first-rate
for the task ahead.
They had been developed to support
battlefield operations.
Luftwaffe had no heavy bombers, and the
feared Stuka was, as we shall see, to
prove almost useless.
The Luftwaffe's commander, Hermann
Göring, had been a Nazi Party faithful
from the start. A decorated fighter ace
in the First World War, he had been
injured in Hitler's abortive attempt to
seize power, the so-called Beer Hall
Putsch.
The medicine Göring took during recovery
from those injuries made him a lifelong
morphine addict.
His influence with Hitler and on
Luftwaffe strategy and spending was
substantial.
Between the first air raid on July the
10th and the middle of August, the
German strategy, essentially Göring's
strategy, was to try and draw British
fighters
>> [music]
>> into combat by attacking convoys at sea.
On August the 8th, over the English
Channel, the RAF lost 16 aircraft,
but shot down 31.
Over the next 3 days, German losses
continued to be greater than those of
the RAF.
And on August the 12th, the focus of the
battle shifted.
Elsewhere in its empire, Britain was
about to fight another action that would
conclude with another forced evacuation
of her troops.
In the early hours of the 3rd of August,
1940, the Italian army crossed the
border between Italian [music] East
Africa and British Somaliland.
The Italians numbered about 24,000.
Opposing them was a British force of
about 4,000 troops,
>> [music]
>> mostly soldiers from India and Africa.
The Somaliland Camel Corps, battalions
from the King's African Rifles, the 3/15
Punjab Regiment, joined during the
campaign by a second Indian regiment and
a Scottish battalion from the Black
Watch. The British had no tanks, armored
cars, or anti-tank weapons.
The smaller force fought a rearguard
action against the advancing Italians
until it was taken off by the Royal Navy
in the early hours of the 18th of
August.
The following day, the Italians moved
down the coast to complete their
conquest of British Somaliland. They
would not stay there long.
Of more lasting significance in the
history books, the month of August was
also the central and most famous month
of the Battle of Britain.
The Luftwaffe attacked the Royal Air
Force directly, targeting airfields and
supporting installations.
Many of the airfields were in the
southeast of England, and the skies over
that part of the country came to be
known as Hellfire Corner.
In that small, vapor trail-laced piece
of sky, more fighter pilots died than in
the whole of the rest of Britain.
Below them on downs and headland, crowds
assembled to cheer each British kill.
On the first day of the attack on the
RAF, three airfields were damaged and
one radar station put out of action. The
next day, August the 13th, the Luftwaffe
launched its greatest attack of the war
to date.
It flew 1,485
sorties,
damaged airfields, though it mistakenly
targeted many that were not fighter
bases,
and lost more than twice as many
aircraft as the RAF.
Losses to the fleet of Junkers 87s, the
Stukas that so terrorized ground forces,
were particularly heavy.
The Stuka was a lethal dive bomber,
but a cumbersome machine in level
flight, both outsped and outmaneuvered
by British fighters.
After further losses, the Stuka was
withdrawn from the Battle of Britain.
And so to Adler Tag, the day that Göring
said was the first day of the decisive
phase of the battle.
The Luftwaffe flew 1,786
sorties against British airfields. It
lost 76 of its aircraft. The RAF lost
35.
The raw figures are misleading.
British losses could to an extent be
made up by the repair of damaged
aircraft returning to their [music]
bases. Damaged German aircraft forced to
land in Britain were lost.
Even more tellingly, British pilots who
bailed out landed in their own fields
and fought again.
German pilots went into captivity.
[music]
More than 900 Luftwaffe pilots who
bailed out over Britain were taken
prisoner.
German aircraft were further
disadvantaged by the limited amount of
time they could spend over their
targets.
The best of their fighters, the
Messerschmitt 109, had an operational
range of only 850 km, much of which was
expended flying to and from the combat
zone.
Even so, it was, as the Duke of
Wellington said of Waterloo, [music] the
nearest run thing you ever saw.
On August the 18th, British losses,
though still smaller than those suffered
by the Luftwaffe, were substantial.
More than 100 RAF pilots had been killed
in a week.
A resource that could not be speedily
replaced.
In one of those strange quirks of fate
that seem to be scattered through the
narratives of war, the near advantage
gained by the Germans on the 18th was
not pressed. Both weather and the
stresses on the German side forced a
four-day pause.
It was during this pause on August the
20th that Winston Churchill gave one of
his best-remembered speeches.
Never in the field of human conflict was
so much owed by so many to so few.
That those who fought and won the Battle
of Britain were indeed few in number
compared to the many who were in their
debt cannot be doubted.
But they were not few compared to the
number of opponents they faced. In most
respects, the fight in the skies above
England was an even contest. [music]
And it was one in which a few of the few
dominated the battle.
Air aces account for a disproportionate
amount of the success.
3 and 1/2% of the RAF's pilots were
responsible for 30% of the claimed
kills.
The first phase of the battle had been
attacks on shipping.
The second attacks on the RAF itself.
After the pause on August the 24th, the
third and decisive [music]
phase began.
On that night, an off-course Heinkel
bomber dropped its bombs in error on an
unintended target.
These were the first bombs to fall on
London.
The bombs had been meant [music] for
military targets in London's suburbs,
but they fell in the center of the city
and did some damage.
The extent to which this mistake
>> [music]
>> and the British reaction to it
determined the future course of the war
can be debated. Perhaps what happened
would have happened in any [music] case.
Perhaps not.
What is sure is that Winston Churchill,
convinced that it had been a deliberate
attack, ordered Berlin to be bombed the
next evening.
On August the 25th, British bombers
reached Berlin and inflicted minimal
property damage.
But the Germans were shocked. Hermann
Göring had assured them that such a
thing could never happen.
But it did.
It happened again on the night of August
the 28th with buildings damaged and
civilians killed. Two nights later, a
third attack occurred.
In Führer Directive 17 of the 1st of
August, in which he [music] laid out his
plans for the conduct of air and sea
warfare against England, Hitler had
specified [music] his targets. They did
not include civilian targets, but at
clause five, he did say, "I reserve to
myself the right to decide on terror
attacks as measures of reprisal."
He now exercised that right.
On September the 4th, he promised, "When
the British Air Force drops two or three
or 4,000 kg of bombs, then we will in
one night drop 150, 200, 300, or 400,000
kg."
"When they declare that they will
increase their attacks on our cities,
then we will raise their cities to the
ground. We will stop the handywork of
those night pirates, so help me God."
The next night, London was attacked and
three days later, on September the 7th,
1940, and for 57 consecutive nights
thereafter, London was bombed.
This was the final phase of the Battle
of Britain. They called it the Blitz.
Thanks to the Anderson shelter, we're
quite safe. I think he dropped a couple
of bombs on us and it shook the shelter
like very well.
But when I had the four boys talk to me,
I was
quite contented. So far I was saying
>> Young women in boiler suits wearing tin
hats patrolled the streets of the
capital blowing whistles and shouting,
"Turn that bloody light off!"
Londoners took to the shelters and slept
in their thousands on the platforms of
underground [music] railway stations.
There was a lot of looting, which you
wouldn't have thought when people went
down the [music] shelters just how easy
to get broke into. They They wouldn't
bother about the raid.
Searchlights lit up the night skies and
anti-aircraft batteries kept up the
tumult of ack-ack against the fleets of
bombers overhead.
But it was all largely show. The
searchlights, some suggested, mainly
helped the bombers find their targets.
And the anti-aircraft batteries are
calculated to have downed one enemy
aircraft for every 30,000 shells fired.
September the 7th, the night of the
first major bombing raid on London, was
a high tide in the English Channel. It
may have been this, so suitable for
invading ships, and possibly other
intelligence received, that caused the
alarm to be sounded.
Troops standing on the defensive
throughout southern England received the
codeword warning that the invasion of
England was expected within 24 hours.
Perhaps surprisingly, at the time of the
greatest threat to the realm and king
and country, the codeword was the name
of a regicide,
Cromwell.
But the Cromwell alert lapsed and no
invasion came.
The bombing offensive continued.
About 15,000 Londoners were killed
during the Blitz and more than a quarter
of a million made homeless.
Buildings that were damaged [music]
included Wren churches, the Houses of
Parliament, and Buckingham Palace,
London home of the king and queen.
On September the 30th, the Luftwaffe
flew its last daylight raid, continuing
thereafter to attack by night.
The British government commissioned
polls to test the mood of the population
and found that 80% remained confident of
a British victory.
The raids [music] grew smaller. The
British officially marked the end of
October as the conclusion of the Battle
of Britain,
although London continued to suffer
heavily.
On November the 14th, the attack on
Coventry marked a new phase in the
German offensive.
Birmingham, Bristol, Southampton,
Sheffield, and Liverpool were all
targeted in November, and British
civilian deaths for that month exceeded
4 and 1/2 thousand.
By now, Britain's Bomber Command was
raining equal, if not greater,
destruction on German cities, as we
shall see in a later episode.
The last night of the Blitz on British
cities
>> [music]
>> would not be until the middle of May
1941, when Hitler needed all of his
strength elsewhere
for the invasion of Russia.
A world war will always draw our
attention across [music] the map as
things of greater or lesser significance
occur, all of which are bricks in the
same edifice.
The autumn of 1940 is, in most
histories, the story of the Battle of
Britain.
But history needs peripheral vision.
On September the 6th, 1940, the day
before the first major bombing raid on
London, King Carol of Romania, a
great-grandchild of Queen Victoria,
abdicated, leaving the country in the
control of another fascist leader, Ion
Antonescu.
On September the 11th, Hitler sent army
and air force reinforcements [music]
uncontested into Romania to protect the
Ploesti oil fields, the only significant
oil wells in Europe. This also [music]
placed the Wehrmacht in a forward base
for operations against the Soviet Union.
But why was Hitler turning his back on
the invasion of Great Britain?
Führer Directive number 16 of July the
16th, 1940, setting in motion
preparations for a landing in Britain,
had stated,
"As England, in spite of her hopeless
military situation, still shows no signs
of willingness to come to terms, I have
decided to prepare, and if necessary, to
carry out a landing operation against
her."
"If necessary."
How could it not be necessary?
Only [music] 3 days later, in a speech
delivered to the Reichstag and broadcast
around the world, Hitler said,
"From London, I now hear a cry.
It's not the cry of the masses people,
[music] but rather of politicians, that
the war must now all the more be
continued."
Hitler said,
"In this hour, I feel compelled to
direct yet another appeal to reason in
England."
Hitler would have preferred peace terms
and the chance to turn to his real
objective, expansion eastwards. British
defiance denied him.
Hitler well understood the risks of an
invasion of the British Isles.
Failure would instantly demolish what
had been built up through his
extraordinary successes since September
1939.
The heads of his air force and navy were
not confident.
There was division among his generals,
and Hitler himself was far from sure of
success.
"On land, I am a hero," he told the
commander of the Kriegsmarine.
"At sea, I am a coward."
There is evidence that the plan for the
invasion, Operation Sea Lion,
was more a political than a military
strategy, a device for strengthening the
peace party in Britain and forcing the
enemy to the negotiating table. In a
sense, for Hitler at least, a bluff.
On the last day of July 1940, Hitler
held a meeting at the Berghof, his home
near Berchtesgaden in the Bavarian Alps.
He was told of the difficulty of
obtaining suitable vessels to carry
invasion troops across the channel and
about the problems of massing troops and
equipment. The German navy argued for a
postponement of the invasion until May
1941.
Hitler postponed the start date, but
only until September the 16th, allowing
the Luftwaffe time to clear the channel
of British warships and the skies over
southeast England of British aircraft,
repeating what had been the first
condition of Führer Directive 16, that
the RAF be so reduced morally and
physically that it is unable to deliver
any significant attack against the
German crossing.
As we have seen in the story of the
Battle of Britain, that had not
happened.
Further, during the Battle of Britain,
the Luftwaffe had made 21 attacks on
Royal Navy torpedo boats operating in
the channel.
It had managed to sink none of them.
Germany had [music] virtually no landing
craft and given barely 2 months to
assemble a sea-going invasion fleet, was
obliged to convert more than 2,000 river
barges.
Only about 800 of these were powered.
The rest would have to be towed by tugs.
When the barges began to be assembled in
channel ports, the RAF's Bomber Command
was ordered to target them.
And about 10% were destroyed at their
moorings.
When Hitler told his commanders that
Operation Sea Lion was indefinitely
postponed,
he cited the Luftwaffe's failure to
obtain air superiority and a general
lack of coordination between the
branches of the German military. But it
is difficult to feel that he ever really
believed in the invasion or its chances
of success.
With the cancellation of Operation Sea
Lion, Great Britain was left an [music]
unsinkable aircraft carrier off the
shores of Western Europe.
On November the 11th, no sirens sounded
in London for the first time since July.
The RAF had lost 915
aircraft, the Luftwaffe
>> [music]
>> 1,733.
Turning his back on the British Isles,
Hitler must have hoped or imagined that
if not defeated, Britain had at least
withdrawn behind her ramparts to bluster
on, but not to interfere in his future
plans.
The danger that he overlooked was that
above all else, the Battle of Britain
ensured the survival of opposition to
the Third Reich.
And that opposition was not a small
island nation off the coast of the
European mainland.
It was an empire.
Events in Europe that had changed the
continent's political complexion through
1940 now had an unexpected and
strategically significant effect on the
opposite side of the globe,
in Asia.
When France fell, its collaborationist
regime, the Vichy government headed by
Marshal Pétain, was as we have learned,
allowed to retain its colonies under the
terms of the peace settlement. And one
of the jewels in that particular
imperial crown was French Indochina, the
modern states of Vietnam, Laos, and
Cambodia.
For expansionist Japan, occupying these
territories was tempting, and in the
case of Vietnam, simply a matter of
walking across the border from occupied
China, which in September of 1940 is
exactly what she did.
Japan's rationale for invasion, which
given there was a war on, was reasonably
legitimate, was that the Nationalist
Chinese were being supplied through the
port of Hai Phong via the
Sino-Vietnamese Railway.
When the Imperial Japanese Army
developed an invasion threat, the Vichy
French administration yielded, and on
September 22nd,
signed an accord which permitted the
Japanese to station several thousand
troops on Vietnamese territory. At the
conference, the Japanese demanded bases
in [music] Indochina and got them.
Meanwhile, the air raids over China
continue. Chungking, the capital, being
bombed again and again.
Within a few hours of the treaty being
signed, columns from the Imperial
Japanese Army moved over the border in
three places and advanced on the
railhead near Lang Son. The next day, on
the 23rd of September, Vichy France
protested the breach of the agreement to
the Japanese government.
On the morning of the 24th, Japanese
aircraft attacked French positions on
the coast. On the 26th,
Japanese forces came ashore south of Hai
Phong and moved on the port.
By the evening of the 26th, fighting had
died down.
Japan was allowed, among other
concessions, three airfields.
When little more than a year later,
Japan launched the offensive designed to
create the Co-Prosperity Sphere, these
and other air bases would prove critical
to providing air support for the
Japanese invasions of the British
colonies of Malaya and Singapore and of
the Dutch East Indies.
As well as Asia, the World War in these
months reached and flared as fierce
fighting in another continent, Africa.
On the 23rd of September, a joint
British Free French adventure was
launched against a Vichy garrison in
West Africa.
By the 25th, the adventure turned into
an embarrassing flop and the forces were
withdrawn.
A Royal Navy force with General Charles
de Gaulle, leader of the Free French on
board, ready to appeal to his
countrymen, approached Dakar, the
capital of modern Senegal.
Leaflets were dropped. Free French
aircraft landed, but instead of being
welcomed, its crews were taken prisoner.
Shore and naval batteries exchanged
fire, and de Gaulle declared that he did
not want to be responsible for Frenchmen
killing Frenchmen.
The task force withdrew.
The affair had been called,
inappropriately, Operation Menace.
September of 1940 also saw the start of
operations in what was to become the
best known and most significant theater
of operations on the African continent,
the North African littoral.
Italo Balbo, marshal of the Italian Air
Force, was one of the architects of
Italian fascism and the only leading
fascist to oppose both anti-Jewish
racial laws and Mussolini's alliance
with Germany.
He was responsible for planning the
invasion of Egypt.
On the 28th of June 1940, coming in to
land at Tobruk, Balbo and his crew were
mistakenly shot down by Italian gunners
and killed. Friendly fire was a poor
beginning to Italy's North African
campaign.
On September the 13th, when it had
become clear that Hitler was not going
to invade Britain, Mussolini ordered the
invasion of Egypt.
By the 16th, the Italians had advanced
the best part of a 100 km beyond the
Libyan border.
Their casualties were 3 and 1/2
thousand, but the British, falling back
into the desert, had taken only 150
casualties.
The British commander, General later
Field Marshal Archibald Wavell, had an
advantage over his opponents in armor.
So, he determined to counterattack and
drive the Italians back beyond the
Libyan border, placing the crucial port
of Tobruk in Allied [music] hands.
Wavell's force of 50,000 pushed the
Italians out of Egypt.
138,000
prisoners and more than 200 guns fell to
the Western Desert Force.
"How many prisoners have you taken?" one
British officer asked another. "Oh,
several acres, I would think." was the
reply.
The story of Italy's war lives in the
popular mind as a story of defeat,
retreat, and surrender.
It is an unfair picture.
What it fails to recognize is the
inferiority of Italy as a fighting
machine.
One statistic tells the tale.
In 1938, Italy's military expenditure
was 746
million dollars.
Germany's was 7 billion 415 million.
Wavell's force typified the strength of
the British Empire. British troops
fought side by side with soldiers from
[music] far away New Zealand and South
Africa and divisions from India. Every
Indian who fought under the British flag
was a volunteer. Their motives for
volunteering were generally practical.
Soldiering was a job that fed and
clothed and housed them.
The soldiers from the Dominions, like
New Zealand, were resolutely patriotic.
They were fighting [music]
for their King George the VI and the
mother country. The war would challenge
the imperial sentiments of the white
Dominions and transform the loyalties of
the Indian troops.
Mussolini, frustrated in North Africa by
Wavell's motley army, had meanwhile, and
in a typically feckless way, turned his
attention elsewhere.
Renewing the Balkan ambitions that had
seen him invade Albania and using that
small country as the springboard,
Mussolini launched an invasion of Greece
on October the 28th.
Il Duce had only informed Hitler of his
intentions the day before the attack.
He met the Führer on the day that
Italian troops moved. This was war by
vanity.
Greece was neutral. Greece was
irrelevant to Hitler's war aims, but
Greece and the Balkans could also,
Mussolini hoped, boost Italian prestige
to match Germany's achievements in the
war.
Hitler, angered by his ally's rashness,
nonetheless offered troops to support
the Italian invasion, but Mussolini
declined. This was to be an Italian
triumph.
Greek Prime Minister General Ioannis
Metaxas, himself a right-wing dictator,
similarly declined Britain's offer of
support. Instead, and unaided, he
mounted a counterattack against the
invading Italians on November the 4th.
Within days, the Italians had been
driven back all the way into Albania.
The reversal owed much to the
conditions, winter, and the terrain, the
northern mountains of Epirus.
The outcome had been foreseen by the
Italian Chief of Staff, Marshal Pietro
Badoglio, who resigned when his counsel
[music] was ignored by Il Duce.
On November the 11th, London's first day
without an air raid warning, the
Italians suffered another setback of a
very different kind.
Venerable British Swordfish torpedo
bombers, operating off of the carrier
HMS [music] Illustrious, attacked the
Italian fleet at its moorings in Taranto
harbor.
The British cheered the first thing in
over a year that had even smelled like a
victory. The Italians counted the cost
of three badly damaged battleships, one
never to put to sea again.
And the Japanese naval attaché in Berlin
hurried to the scene to take detailed
notes of what a carrier-borne attack on
a fleet at anchor could do.
On December the 4th, 5 weeks after the
invasion of Greece, the Italian Under
Secretary of State for War, General
Ubaldo Soddu, was recommending an
armistice.
Winter had already frozen military
activity with the armies facing each
other on what had formerly been Italian
territory.
In January, Hitler would announce
military support for his Axis partner,
marching to Italy's aid firstly in
Greece and then in North Africa.
Also in January, the British would
launch their [music] offensive against
the Italians in the Horn of Africa, in
Somaliland and in Abyssinia, whose
emperor, Haile Selassie, the Italians
had chased [music] from his throne.
But much greater events were to occur in
the year ahead.
As 1941 dawned, President Franklin
Delano Roosevelt broadcast to the
American people.
"My friends," he said, "this is not a
fireside chat on war. It is a talk on
national security."
He told the international audience, for
many were listening around the world on
shortwave radios, "We must be the great
arsenal of democracy."
And he concluded, "We have no excuse for
defeatism. We have every good reason for
hope. Hope for peace, yes, and hope for
the defense of our civilization and for
the building of a better civilization in
the future."
In the next episode of The Price of
Empire, it is the year 1941, the year
that was to transform the war and the
world in a way that few single years can
be said to have affected the narrative
of history.
Germany would invade the Soviet Union
and Japan would force the United States
into the war at a place called Pearl
Harbor.